<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Spadacrene Dunelmensis, or, A short treatise of an ancient medicinal fountain or vitrioline spaw near the city of Durham together with the constituent principles, virtues and use thereof / by E.W. ...</title>
            <author>E. W. (Edward Wilson)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66543</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38665</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17882348</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17882348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106707</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66543)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106707)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1110:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Spadacrene Dunelmensis, or, A short treatise of an ancient medicinal fountain or vitrioline spaw near the city of Durham together with the constituent principles, virtues and use thereof / by E.W. ...</title>
                  <author>E. W. (Edward Wilson)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistola dedicatoria" signed: Odoardus Wilsonus.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mineral waters --  Therapeutic use --  England --  Durham.</term>
               <term>Health resorts --  England --  Durham.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106707:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106707:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Spadacrene Dunelmenſis:</hi> OR A SHORT TREATISE Of an Ancient <hi>MEDICINAL FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTAIN</hi> OR VITRIOLINE SPAW <hi>Near the City of</hi> DURHAM.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> With the Conſtituent Principles, Virtues and Uſe thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> E. W. <hi>Doctor of Phyſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Godbid,</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106707:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106707:2"/>
            <head>REVERENDO DOMINO D<hi rend="sup">no</hi> JOHANNI SUDBURIO, Decano Dunelmenſi optime merito, <hi>Nec non ampliſſimis ejuſdem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationis Prebendariis jugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obſervantia colendiſſimis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>EXpectabunt fortè nonnulli (ampliſſimi Domini) me in hoc proloquio gratiam benevolentiamque veſtram aucupaturum veſtrae laudis (ut mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris eſt) encomia texere velle. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet equidem ampla dicendi materia, ſpatioſus dilatandi Campus, ſed meis ut fateor viribus impar, &amp; veſtris ſane virtutibus ſupervacane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;
<pb facs="tcp:106707:3"/> altius inſonuit virtus veſtra quam ut tubis indigeat, clarius e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luxit quam ut facem praeferam. Eſt mihi profectò jubilandi ſimul ac con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulandi ſed non pro meritis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris collaudandi facultas, plus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtis praeſtatiſque opere, quam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamo me decet explicare. Accedo itaque non tanquam aliquid honoris collaturus, ſed beneficium poſtulatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus; ut nimirum jugis haec noſtra acidula agrorum Dunelmenſium ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigua, veſtro pariter favore ac pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trocinio effloreſcat. Hoc tantum Enimvero poſuit Deus morbum ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul ac medelam, illum nobis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit peccatum, hanc libere profudit mundi piaculum. Jacuiſſemus alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin in ſordibus iniquitatum, &amp; truculentam adhuc hoſtium ſuſtinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſemus atrocitatem, niſi <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſalutiferum nobis itidem conciliaſſet medicamentum. Oh immenſam amoris flagrantiam, oh
<pb facs="tcp:106707:3"/> inauditum pietatis argumentum. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum enim vero inter tot tantaſque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum creatarum varietates nihil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis cedit in humani generis conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vationem, quam faecundum illud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarum ſeminarium: hinc eſt quod Spiritus Domini ferebatur ſuper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quas, Haebraicè <hi>Merahepheth</hi> incuba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat aquas, ob inſignem vitalitatis virtutem à Spiritu Sancto in aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum procreatione conceſſam; unde non immerito Chimici jactitant, ab aqua ſunt omnia, &amp; in aquam redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur omnia. Quapropter (Colen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimi) accipite hunc noſtrum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellum votúmque tanquam amoris ſimul ac debitae venerationis ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, quo plurimos adhuc ſemper fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licius invicem ſuccedentes annos, &amp; tandem, ſero licèt, aeternae faelicitatis gaudium ſupplicat apprecaturque</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Humilimus dominationum veſtrarum ſervus ODOARDUS WILSONUS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106707:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>AS the powerful Hand of God made all things for the uſe of man, ſo was it His Divine Will and Pleaſure, that he ſhould be compleatly furniſhed with all ſuch Remedies as principally concern'd the perfect preſervation of his health. Hence it is, that all things created have their peculiar Medicinal faculty: Every particular mixt Body, virtually
<pb facs="tcp:106707:4"/> reſpects one part or other of our human Bodies, and by a marvellous ſtrange Character points out that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively it is appointed to maintain, nay it is as it were with a certain weight carried unto that with which it holds an amical and natural corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence. And becauſe our human conſtitution conſiſts of many ſulphureous, nitrous, ſaline, vitrioline, and oleagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous parts, thence it is that Spaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waters, which perfectly partake of thoſe mixtures, perform ſuch admirable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects upon diſaffected Bodies. But ſome may ſay, and that truly, that 'tis a great controverſie among the Metalla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopical Philoſophers, whether Metals can truely and properly be mixed with water? To which I ſay, that the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is confuſaneous, though not perfect, as appears in <hi>Aqua Regia,</hi> in which Gold it ſelf is reſolved into inſenſible Atoms, and even ordinary water ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of a virtual mixture at leaſt, as
<pb facs="tcp:106707:5"/> Experience evidenceth in Chalybiate waters. Again, Minerals are not ſo ſolid and compact in their ſubterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous veins, nor have they their due perfection, but of a more moiſt, ſoft, and glebiſh conſiſtence, ſo that by a cauſtick water, or ſpirituous ſulphureous liquor, even the Metalline Spirits are eaſily ſeparated, and their raments communicated, however a ſpecifick vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is certainly commixed, and a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous propriety at leaſt imbibed. If Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals may be thus incorporated, much more may Minerals, which are only Metals <hi>in fieri.</hi> And therefore with ſome probability we may ſay, that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral waters may not only be impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with a virtual propriety exiſting in the Spirits, but alſo with the very ſubſtantial particles of the ſaid Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals. Now the next, and indeed the chief thing to be enquired into, is the giving an exact account of Mineral waters, ſince upon this hinge depends
<pb facs="tcp:106707:5"/> the whole ſafety of ſuch as drink them. Therefore I ſhall as briefly as may be diſcharge this incumbency. Firſt then, the virtues and properties of theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are known from the mixture of their terreſtrial Glebes and Minerals, and the manner of knowing and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing them is twofold; the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends meerly on the ſenſes, the other (which Philoſophers call <hi>à poſteriori</hi>) is gathered from the recrements which their channels leave behind them. Now there is an innate faculty in the nature of Man, to know things <hi>ex evidenter apparentibus &amp; ſenſibilibus,</hi> and therefore the eſſence or ſubſtance of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral waters are to be known, how they are differenced in their qualities from ſimple waters, by their colour, taſte, ſmell, and ſometimes quality of touch. Theſe virtues, thus diſtinguiſhed, are either elementary, and ſuch as perform their operations by the firſt qualities of hot, cold, moiſt, and dry; or ſpecifick,
<pb facs="tcp:106707:6"/> ſuch as ſome call heavenly, as far ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing both the power of all elements, and much tranſcending the reach of our ſenſes, being ſuch in their effects, as leave nothing leſs than wonders in our underſtanding; which unintelligible vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, if it exert it ſelf in any mixt body, it's principally obſervable in Spaws; neither is there any Fountain that is not favourably breathed with ſome Divine Rays, and affected with ſome ſingular and peculiar good, the finding out of which, is ſo much more difficult, as the cloſet of their cauſes is inacceſſible. This infinity of variety congeminates difficulties, in ſo much that Nature enthrones her ſelf in no mixt body ſo gloriouſly as in this her <hi>Paranymphs</hi> Kingdom; witneſs thoſe innumerable different <hi>ſpecies</hi> of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which are ſo many as there are different <hi>ſpecies</hi> of terreſtrial Glebes, Minerals, Metals, liquid and concrete Juyces, which as they exceed Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick,
<pb facs="tcp:106707:6"/> ſo likewiſe do the waters par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of them, eſpecially if the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral combinations with their ſeveral mixtures be duly conſidered. Hence it is that <hi>Seneca, lib. 3. nat. quaeſt. de Aquis, Ad rem inquit ſeriam, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem, immenſam acceſſimus, ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemus &amp; opus neſcio an ſuperabile, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Pliny, lib. 31. cap. 1. Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimas aquarum vires differentiaſque conſpicatus cunctas, exclamat, quis mortalium enumerare queat?</hi> Some honeſt Philoſophers have been affrighted hereat, becauſe an infinity cannot be fathom'd; others taking heart have ſaid, that <hi>miſcellae quibus aquae tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur &amp; praedominium qualita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſenſuum officio experimento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque poſſunt quidem (etiamſi dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultate) comperiri.</hi> Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all theſe difficulties, <hi>Non ita deterremur</hi> (ſaith that Object of the Worlds wonder, <hi>Kircherus,) ut pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde nobis haſtam abjiciendi animus
<pb facs="tcp:106707:7"/> ſit; eſt aliquid prodire tenus, ſi non datur ultra.</hi> Let us wiſh therefore we had <hi>Pliny</hi>'s <hi>fontem Leontinum cujus aquas qui bibiſſet ſcientem evadere medicum recitat,</hi> and being arm'd with this phantaſtical conceit, take upon us to tell you, that all wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are either mixed with different Glebes of terreſtrial matter, wherein we comprehend all ſpecies of Earth, or with the different ſorts of Salts which are called concrete Juyces, and ſo there will be as many different ſpecies of waters, as there are different ſorts of Salts; or they are adjoyned to the different ſpecies of liquid juyces, ſuch as are unctuous and fat as Bitumen, or not unctuous, as are all ſtrong cauſtick waters; or they are mixed with the Metalline Bodies, and ſo inveſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the ſame nature they are ting'd withall; or laſtly they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied with divers kinds of ſtony Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inalities, ſuch as that at <hi>Knarsbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106707:7"/> Out of the manifold compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of all which, ariſeth that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable variety of waters, which if you conjugate according to the principles of Art combinatory, there will be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to renowned <hi>Kircher,</hi> 479001600 different ſpecies, that is, four hundred ſeventy nine millions one thouſand and ſix hundred ſorts of waters. Let none therefore wonder, if we be not dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically poſitive in our Aſſertions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Virtues of waters, ſince no leſs than an approach to infinity can determin the various complications of Mineral, Metalline, and Saline Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, with which theſe are impowred; yet ſo far as <hi>ſenſata experientia</hi> and natural Philoſophy, which is an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental Chymiſtry and mechanical knowledge of things, can carry us, we may ſafely believe, as one well obſerves, <hi>Spagyria ſola eſt ſpeculum veri intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus, monſtratque tangere &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere veritatem.</hi> I ſhall not therefore
<pb facs="tcp:106707:8"/> go about to obumbrate the Truth under the veil of obſcure Appellations, nor attach other Mens Reaſonings of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor ſing Matins and Evening<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſong to my own <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by a ſort of big and exotique expreſſions, calling, with <hi>Baſilius Valentinus, Hippocrates</hi>'s <hi>Ignis</hi> and <hi>Aqua, Gladiatores</hi> and <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Phalaia;</hi> nor with <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> ſhrowding the ſame Inſtruments of Nature under the names of divers Spirits, <hi>Spiritus alter trahit, alter protrudit, idem autem uterque facit;</hi> nor with <hi>Helmont,</hi> ſtiling the animal, vital, and natural Spirits of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients by that bugbear name of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeus,</hi> which can be nothing elſe but the moſt fine, volatile, and Aetherial parts of the Blood, contained in the Veins, Nerves, and Arteries. But I ſhall endeavour clearly and ſpagyrically to demonſtrate the true Principles and Conſtituents of this our Spaw in our following Diſcourſe. <hi>Soli illi docent
<pb facs="tcp:106707:8"/> qui per cauſas &amp; principia docent.</hi> In the interim, for more clearneſs ſake, I ſhall ſet down (ſince the firſt qualities give us but an uncertain and conjectural rule of finding out the true Eſſences of waters) a threefold manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, for diſcovering in general the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine and true mixtures of all Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinal waters.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The firſt is by Concoction, thus:</p>
            <p>Take a glaſs veſſel, or an earthen one glazed, and boil therein your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral water, 'till a third part be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, afterwards let it ſettle well for three days ſpace for ſeparating its <hi>Faeces,</hi> then take a groſs thick Cloth fit for filtration, and ſhape it in the form of an inverted Pyramis, hang the pointed pyramidal end in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let the other extremity firſt being moiſtened hang down without the veſſel; and it will come to paſs, that the moiſtened end hanging without the veſſel, ſhall draw the water in the
<pb facs="tcp:106707:9"/> other extremity of the filter, which was plung'd in the water, and thus by little and little all the water, and only the pure water, ſhall be drawn out, the ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment remaining, which being expos'd to the Sun, you may thence diſcover the mixture of the Minerals.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſecond way of judging Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral mixtures in Spaw waters is by eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, thus:</p>
            <p>Take a glaſs veſſel with a large ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, place it midway deep in another earthen veſſel full of ſand, and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate all the moiſture, and dry the ſediment or <hi>Faeces</hi> in the Sun, and you ſhall know the mixtures by the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the Mineral particles; the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of this way of trial is, that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the water the Mineral Spirits flye away, which happeneth not in the former nor in this following way of proceeding.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The third, and indeed the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureſt way, of finding out the nature of
<pb facs="tcp:106707:9"/> Mineral waters is by diſtillation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hereby not only the groſſer particles of every Mineral, but even the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant ſpirits and vaporous are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly made known, and it is thus:</p>
            <p>Prepare a furnace with vent-holes, and place therein a proper earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel full of ſand, in this ſand another veſſel filled with water up to the middle, <hi>v. g.</hi> a <hi>Cucurbita,</hi> or glaſs ſtill bottom, with a prety ſtrait mouth, to this <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curbita</hi> you muſt fit a <hi>Capitellum</hi> with a noſe or an alembick roſtrated, being well luted that nothing can expire, and to this noſe of your <hi>Capitellum</hi> you muſt adapt another <hi>Fiſtula,</hi> or glaſs pipe, well luted, which pipe muſt run through a wooden veſſel full of cold water, this done, put fire to your furnace, and draw off all the water, and what remains of ſediment expoſe to the Sun to be dryed; which done, for diſſolving the ſeveral ſpecies of the Minerals proceed thus: Expoſe the ſediment upon a poliſh'd Iron
<pb facs="tcp:106707:10"/> Table red hot, and being mixed with water the Chalk, Marble, and <hi>Gypſum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> or Plaiſter will not be burnt, but after all the others are burnt, they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main more ſhining white than former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Gypſum</hi> preſently, but the Chalk and Marble require more time. If there be Brimſtone, it diſcovers it ſelf by its accuſtomed ſtrong ſent; Salt and Niter ſparkle, Salt with crackling but Niter without any. If Ceruſs be there, it is turn'd into an intenſe red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, an evident ſign of Lead; Allum being melted turns white like Milk, and Vitriol darkly reddiſh like Colcothar; and this effect had the ſediment of this our Spaw-water, without any ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous ſmell at all; the <hi>Faeces</hi> whereof I gathered both by Coction and Diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, but leſs remained of <hi>Faeces</hi> by Evaporation, an evident ſign of the ſpirituous ſubtilty of the Mineral mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Now as to the diſcovery of Metalline
<pb facs="tcp:106707:10"/> tinctures in waters, they are known by their proper excrements and corruption of their ſediments, therefore the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proceeding is thus:</p>
            <p>If Metal be in waters, infuſe the ſediment of the Metalline water in ſome Chymical corroſive water, or in ſome generouſly ſharp Vinegar, and if you ſee an Ironiſh ruſt upon the ſediment, you may be ſure of the mixture of Iron with the water; and ſo of Braſs, Gold, and all others.</p>
            <p>Thus have I given ſome Remarques in general, and hinted only by the by at my greateſt concern, the Conſtituents of our Spaw, of which hereafter; I ſhall now only beg pardon, if I make an uſeful, though as to my preſent inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſomewhat impertiment digreſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Raimundus Lullius</hi> tells us of an Apparition he had, of Madam <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>'s weeping unto him, for Mens en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to diſcover her Secrets, and proſtitute them to the hands of her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb facs="tcp:106707:11"/> meaning the Illiterate. And <hi>Beguinus</hi> gives advice, and makes it his requeſt, that Phyſitians would not acquaint Mountebanks, and bold Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders into the Practice of Phyſick, with his Antimonial Preparations, <hi>Ab uſu</hi> (ſays he) <hi>horum ut illegitimorum ſe abſtineant.</hi> And that great Chymiſt <hi>Libavius,</hi> as well as Galeniſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of that fatal liberty in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Phyſick, <hi>Illud Cavendum</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ne audaculi imperiti in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicando id adhibeant quod eſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicorum circumſpectiſſimorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitatiſſimorumque, veluti ſi eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia ex ſublimato &amp; regulo fiat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. tu qui imperitus es methodi medendi &amp; impudens, nec tibi, nec aliis horum permitte uſum cum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meritate. Nam nobiles medicinae in manu temerarii hominis ſunt ut culter vel fax ardens in manu pueri aut dementis.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">And doubtleſs (ſaith Dr. <hi>Caſtle</hi>) as there is more danger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:106707:11"/> that a Child may do miſchief with a knife of ſteel rather than with one of bone; ſo the hazard that Men run of their lives in taking Chymical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies at the hands of Empericks, is much the greater, by how much the Preparations which they uſe are of more force and virtue And upon this</q> occaſion, it will be no grand preſumption (good Reader) eſpecially being back'd by authority and truth, to tell you of the ſtrange and ſhameleſs impudency that a great many, Fanaticks eſpecially, aſſume in the Practice of Phyſick, holding all Learning unneceſſary, and <hi>Latin</hi> the Language of the Beaſt. Univerſities (ſay they) teach nothing but jejune, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, and chymerical Conceptions, and their Licenſe <hi>ad practicandum</hi> ſignifies no more than a ſet form of Prayer does in Devotions. Thus they trample all Learning under foot, and ſet no greater eſtimate upon Philoſophy, than ſome make conſcience in killing one by inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;
<pb facs="tcp:106707:12"/> whilſt they by their myſterious and aenigmatical canting, hard words, and God knows what unintelligible, and indeed nonſenſical expreſſions, draw their poor Patients, the vulgar Rabble eſpecially, into an admiration of their high parts and knowledge in Phyſick. Thus they ſteal though illegally into practice, and cunningly pick Mens purſes with applauſe and ſatisfaction. This promiſcuous toleration ſharpen'd Dr. <hi>Caſtle</hi>'s Pen, telling us, That our Nation is of late grown ſo fond of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſticks in Phyſick as they are of thoſe in Divinity, and ignorance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſome Men is become as neceſſary a qualification for the practice of Phyſick, as it is for Preaching. <q rend="margQuotes">I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve (ſays he) that the delight which the Vulgar (nay and ſome wiſe Men) take in being cheated by Quacks and Mountebanks, proceeds from any principle in Nature which inclines them to it, but rather think it to be
<pb facs="tcp:106707:12"/> cauſed from Impoſtors being more indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in deluding the world, than the true Artiſts are in undeceiving it.</q> And indeed this growing evil, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the method of the Ancients, and beſt endeavours (after a ſtrict exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination at the Univerſities) of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duate Phyſitians, and following the whimſies and follies of ſome phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Pſeudo-Chymiſts,</hi> is like the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericans,</hi> who barter Gold and Silver for Beads and Glaſs. To this purpoſe I could inſtance, but am not deſirous to make any perſonal reflection, in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular paſſage here in <hi>Durham,</hi> of one who very ſeriouſly ſaid he was a <hi>beguifted Apothecary:</hi> I imagin he is the ſame now in Phyſick and Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery; <hi>haud aliquid in ullo.</hi> But of this no more, only give me leave to tell ſuch precarious Practitioners, that their petulancy is too ſawcy, in preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſo magiſterially to direct in Caſes where life and death are ſo nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd,
<pb facs="tcp:106707:13"/> eſpecially when as neither Lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning nor Reading, nor lawful Authority gives any encouragement thereunto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'Tis not ſufficient for a conſcientiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Phyſitian, to know Receipts, how to purge, vomit, or ſweat, neither is it only requiſit, that he underſtand the nature and force of the Remedy, but likewiſe the conſtitution and ſtrength of the Patient, and the nature, times, and motion of the Diſeaſe, it being certain, that the ſame Remedy in the ſame Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, which advantagiouſly may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to day, may perniciouſly deſtroy to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morrow. Therefore let me admoniſh thee, good Reader, not to credit too much thoſe touchy headed Chymiſts, who pretend to <hi>Panacaea</hi>'s, Univerſal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, Secrets, and ſuch like whimſical Remedies, but let their <hi>Materia Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica</hi> be wholly founded upon Experience, <hi>Crebro ſingularium tentamine,</hi> by a frequent tryal of each Medicine: And this was the opinion of the learned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:106707:13"/> 
               <hi>Varandaeus</hi> to Dr. <hi>Primroſe,</hi> telling him, that thoſe Remedies are the beſt which are no ſecrets but beſt known, as being confirmed by more certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, conſidering that credulity is in no Art of ſo dangerous a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as in Phyſick. And therefore the learned Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> in his <hi>Scepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Chymiſt,</hi> warns us not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in believing Chymical Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; <q rend="margQuotes">For (ſays he) as the obſcurity of what ſome Writers deliver makes it difficult to be underſtood, ſo the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs of too many others makes it unfit to be relied on. What circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection</q> ought therefore to be uſed in managing the Cure of a Diſeaſe? when the leaſt inadvertency or errour in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, coſts many Men no leſs than the price of their lives. And to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is the Dialogue betwixt <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Phaedrius:</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">If any one ſhould tell me, (ſays <hi>Socrates</hi>) Truly I know how to apply thoſe things to the body, with
<pb facs="tcp:106707:14"/> which I can, when I pleaſe, make i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hot or cold, vomit and purge, and cauſe other evacuations, upon the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of which, I profeſs my ſelf a Phyſitian, and affirm, that any Man inſtructed with this knowledge may be one; what anſwer do you think a ſober Man would return to him? Truly (ſaid <hi>Phaedrius</hi>) none at all, but ask him, whether he likewiſe underſtands to whom, and when, and in what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion every one of theſe Medicines are to be given, of which if he be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, the man muſt certainly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be mad, who upon the ſcore, either of gleanings from Authors, or for having been preſent at the Cures of ſome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, and underſtanding nothing ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidly and rationally of the Art, thinks he is preſently become a Phyſitian.</q> Many ſafe Medicines have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by being given by Emperiks, and have kill'd inſtead of curing, they not ſuiting them to the temper, age, ſex, and
<pb facs="tcp:106707:14"/> ſtrength of their Patients: This <hi>Senner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> witneſſeth, telling us of two Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren killed by two old Women with Oyl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Amber; the one broke out all over the body, as if ſcalding water had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oured upon it, and preſently dyed; the other dyed vomiting and purging. Nay, that very ſafe Remedy <hi>Mercurius dulcis</hi> (call'd by Sir <hi>Theodore Meyern Calomelanos,</hi> from one <hi>Fair-black</hi> his man, who prepared it for him) has been to ſome conſtitutions accompanied with hazardous ſymptoms; and no <hi>Pty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oliſmus,</hi> or Salivation, can be given, it being from Mercury, without a great deal of circumſpection. I therefore hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily adviſe our new-coyn'd Phyſitians, ſince they muſt be dabbling, not too much to Idolize <hi>Monſieur Mercury,</hi> nor fond too much of their late skill in <hi>Salivation,</hi> thoſe that know it full out as well as they muſt, tell them by way of friendly advice, that it ought to be given to none but ſuch as are <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106707:15"/>
            <p>And now, good Reader, I have even wearied thee out, and therefore will haſten to my matter, and conclude this Preface with <hi>Hippocrates, Qui vocat medicinam omnium artium nobiliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimam, ſed propter ignorantiam eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui eam male exercent, eſſe om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium viliſſimam; fundamentum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim, quo pedem figunt, non habent, de quibus etiam Seneca, ſemper di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, nunquam ad veritatem perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niunt;</hi> and the reaſon is, becauſe they have no guide for direction, they are ſo enthuſiaſtically wiſe, they ſcorn a Maſter to inſtruct them methodically in the true fundamentals of Phyſick, but ſhooting at random, with all their induſtry no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is produced but <hi>rudis indigeſta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> moles.</hi> And the ſame Author going on tells us, <hi>Ignorantia eſt quae omne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum in medicina generat, adeo ut medicus nunc paſſim ludibrio expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitus, comicis in facetias &amp; mundo in proverbium ivit.</hi> And beſide the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
<pb facs="tcp:106707:15"/> of ſome, the malicious detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns of others, even among our ſelves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ender us contemptible, which very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing occaſions a good <hi>Galeno-Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al</hi> Author to break out into exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, thus: <hi>Ubi <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quam tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opere commendat Hyp. noſtro ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo unus vilipendit alterum, dicta &amp; facta taxat, rixatur à tergo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>radicit, quae non intelligit, ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum apud ignaram plebem extollit ſordida ſpe lucelli.</hi> Pardon this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ergy, I ſhall expatiate no more upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſordid a ſubject; what I am now to ſay, ſhall be Obſervations from Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments, and therefore ought to force a faith, as to matter of Fact; if the manner be but any way well, it is well, ſo farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, E. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:106707:16"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106707:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SPADACRENE</hi> Dunelmenſis.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Of ſimple Water, its qualities and uſe.</head>
               <p>THat there is naturally pure ſimple water to be found, without any heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial admixture at all, is paradoxical, therefore by ſimple water I only mean ſuch as hath a proper colour, taſte, ſmell, weight, and conſiſtence, thin, light, cold, and moiſt, and no other thing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106707:17"/> either by ſenſes or effects: And 'tis requiſite that water ſhould have theſe qualities, in regard of the many and neceſſary uſes of it, both for Men, Beaſts, Vegetables, and Minerals; in ſo much as there is no living for any Creature where there is no water. <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> begins <hi>Pindar</hi>'s <hi>Olymp. Od.</hi> 1. It was our firſt drink to quench thirſt, and by its tenuity diſtributes our nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment as a Vehicle, nay after the invention of Wine it was uſually mixed therewith, as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſaith of <hi>Bacchus,</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Poculaque inventis Acbeloia miſcuit uvis.</q>
               <p>I could heartily wiſh, that even <hi>Bacchus</hi> himſelf might herein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our Preſident, eſpecially ſince in other things he hath taught our too docil world, as <hi>v. g.</hi> by the ſame
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106707:17"/> purity and tenuity of the parts of water, how to make Beverages of ſundry ſorts. The <hi>Aegyptians</hi> have their <hi>Zythum,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> their <hi>Cerea,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> their <hi>Coffee,</hi> and we our Ale and Beer; all extracted by water, the fitteſt Menſtruum for receiving the Faculties of all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments and nouriſhment, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the ſecond qualities of mixt Bodies, and for this reaſon was it called <hi>Panſpermia.</hi> That ſimple wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is cold, is without queſtion, for being heated accidentally, it ſoon returns to its natural coldneſs, the cauſe of heat being removed; but whether it be colder than Air is much to be doubted. I ſhall not now undertake the determining, whether Air be bred of water ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally, or whether it be not a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct ſubſtance of it ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives only watery vapours, and after mature condenſation in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106707:18"/> middle Region, exonerates it ſelf by Rain, Hail, Snow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Only thus much I dare affirm, that the Sun beams are of much more force to elevate ſubſtances from the Earth, than moſt imagin, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe that hold the materiality of the Air to be from water, are not in opinion altogether paradoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, but veriſimilitudinary. And to prove this vigorous extraction of the Sun from ſublunary Bodies, give me leave to give you an inſtance of what <hi>Athanaſius Kircherus</hi> (whoſe company much honour'd me from <hi>Marſeilles</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi>) moſt faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, <hi>in Magicae Paraſtaticae, Paraſtiſi I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Naturae,</hi> thus:</p>
               <q>Morgana Rheginorum.</q>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">In the midſt of Summer, when the Sun boils the <hi>Tyrrhene</hi> Ocean with moſt fervent rays, then is it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106707:18"/> that wanton Nature entertains the wondering Eyes of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Rhegium,</hi> (a Town in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labria,</hi> moſt ancient, and no leſs famous, for having been the Seat of many Philoſophers) with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Spectacle in the Air. There may you (whether with more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light or wonder is not ſoon deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined) behold a ſpatious Theatre in the vaporous Air, adorned with great variety of Scenes and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toptrick Repreſentations, the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of Caſtles, Palaces, and other Buildings of excellent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecture, with ſundry ranges of Pillars, preſented according to the Rules of Perſpective. This Scene withdrawn upon the Sayling by of the Cloud, there ſucceeds ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherein by way of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Landskip were exhibited ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Woods, Groves of Cypreſs, Orchards with variety of Trees,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106707:19"/> but thoſe artificially planted in uniform rows, like a perfect Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanx, large Meadows with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Men, and herds o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Beaſts walking, feeding, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching upon them: And all theſe with ſo great variety of reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent colours, ſo admirable a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of light and darkneſs and all their motions and geſture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo counterfeited to the life, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to draw a Landskip of equal per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection ſeems to humane Natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> altogether impoſſible.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now to our purpoſe: This pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raſtatical Phantaſm was not cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Cloud from any reflected ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pearance of any ſuch things, eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the ſhore or adjacent fields, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe no ſuch thing was there which indeed increaſed the ardou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of curioſity in renowned <hi>Kircher</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> croſs over from <hi>Meſſina</hi> to <hi>Rhegiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> at the uſual time of the apparition
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106707:19"/> where he detected the Cauſes of the whole Phaenomenon; obſerving firſt, the Shores ſubjacent to the Mountain called <hi>Tinna,</hi> as alſo the bottom of the Sea, to be covered with ſhining Sand, being the frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Selenites,</hi> Antimony, and other pellucid concretions devolved from the eminent parts of the Land and contiguous Hills, that are rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fraught with Veins of thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals. Then he obſerved, that theſe tranſlucid Sands being, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Vapours from the Sea and Shore, exhaled into the Air by the intenſe fervour of the Sun, did coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs into a Cloud, in all points re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent to a perfect polyedrical or multangular Looking-glaſs, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſuperficies of the reſpondent Granates making a multiplication of the Species; and that theſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing opacated behind by groſs and impervious Vapours, directly facing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106707:20"/> the Mountains, did make reflection of the various Images of Objects, reſpective to their various poſitions, to the eye. The ſeveral rows of Pillars in the Aerial Scene are cauſed by one ſingle Pillar erected on the Shore, for being by a manifold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection from the various ſuperficies of the tralucent particles, opacated on the hinder part by denſe vapours in the ſpeculary Meteor, it is mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied even to infinity; no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, than if one ſingle Image, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited betwixt two polyedrical Loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glaſſes confrontingly diſpoſed, is ſo often repercuſſed or reflected from ſuperficie to ſuperficie, that it exhibiteth to the eye almoſt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite multitude of Images exactly conſimilar. Thus alſo doth one Man ſtanding on the Shore become a whole Army in the Cloud, one Beaſt a whole Herd, and one Tree à thick ſet Grove<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Some perhaps
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106707:20"/> may judge this aſſertion, of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of thoſe ſhining Grains of Vitreous Minerals into the Air by the meer attraction of the Sun, and the coalition of them there with the Cloud of Vapours, to be too large a morſel to be ſwallowed by any throat, but that cormorant one of credulity. If ſo, all we require of them is only to conſider, that Hairs, Straws, grains of Sand, fragments of Wool, and ſuch like feſtucous Bodies, are frequently found immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Hailſtones, which ſurely are ſufficient arguments, that thoſe things were firſt elevated by the Beams of the Sun, recoiling from the Earth into the middle Region of the Air, and then coagulated with the Vapours, condenſed into a Cloud, and frozen in its deſcent. The truth hereof is evicted by the conſpiring teſtimonies of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authors, whoſe Pens are not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106707:21"/> dipt in the fading Ink of an unjuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable Tradition, nor their Minds deluded with the affectation of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous wonders. Now to reaſſume the debate, I ſhall only give my judgment of the temperature of the Air, as to heat or cold, and that it is of its own nature cold is moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, (though <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> concluded the contrary, from its efficient cauſe which rarified it.) The <hi>Stoicks</hi> were alſo of this opinion, becauſe they made the matter of Air to be water; and this is alſo confirmed by its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to coldneſs (as formerly was ſaid of water) in caſe it be acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally heated; and we know that under the <hi>Zona torrida,</hi> ſo long as the Sun is within their Horizon and ſtrikes the Air with its perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Beams, 'tis exceeding hot, but after Sun-ſet the Air reaſſumes its natural coldneſs 'till Sun-riſe again, nay though <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> thought it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106707:21"/> uninhabitable becauſe of the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of heat, yet being the days and nights are there of the ſame length, <hi>Joſephus Acoſta</hi> concludes that the only Paradiſe upon Earth is under or near the Aequinoctial; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can there any other reaſon be given why the Mountains which reach the middle Region of the Air are continually cold, and moſtly covered with Snow, but becauſe they wanting the reflection of the Sun-beams, the Air doth then enjoy its natural qualification. As for that whimſey of an <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi> in the middle Region from the Element of Fire above, and the reflection of the Beams beneath, it's an equal phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſm with the Man in the Moon, who would have hot ſitting if Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Fire were immediately un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. But this opinion is explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and if ſuch Fire were, it would rather heat than cool the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106707:22"/> Air. Is not the Air moſt cold near the Poles, where the long abſence of the Sun, and its oblique Beams when preſent, give way to its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural coldneſs? Nay 'tis very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that it is colder than water, ſince we ſee by a condenſative fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty it congeals water into Ice, Snow, Hail, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which certainly is from the Air, being that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground, where the water is not free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ventilated with Air, there's no congelation; neither do I think other but the great coldneſs that's in Ice and Snow, depends meerly upon the mixture of Air, which being <hi>per minima</hi> interwoven with Salnitrous particles, is heightened to ſuch a degree of coldneſs as makes it vigorous for producing a conge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative effect. That water is moſt moiſt is the opinion of <hi>Galen,</hi> and very probably true, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s reaſon to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106707:22"/> concluding Air to be moſt moiſt, becauſe it's hardly contained within its bounds, which indeed is by reaſon of its tenuity and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contiguity of parts, being that dry exhalations extend themſelves as well as moiſt vapours, and as den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity compacts, ſo rarity cauſeth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion. I ſhall need ſay no more of the qualities which ſimple water ought to have, being ſuch as are every where obvious in Authors, and the ſenſes will diſcover either by taſte, colour, ſmell or touch, or elſe the effects will make manifeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106707:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the Original of ſimple Waters and Springs in general.</head>
               <p>GReat controverſies have been betwixt the <hi>Stoicks</hi> and <hi>Peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticks,</hi> and are yet amongſt the Moderns, concerning the original of true Springs, which are no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than thoſe of mixt waters. All difficulties and arguments touching this grand Debate are reducible into three heads; for either our perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and laſting Springs, called <hi>Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes perennes,</hi> proceed from vapours congealed by cold in the ſecond Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Air, and ſo fall down upon the Earth in Rain, Snow, or Hail; or they are ingendred in the bowels of the Earth; or they are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106707:23"/> percolated through ſandy ſubterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal channels from the Sea. For the firſt, it may be granted that divers Springs and Rivers receive ſupply of waters from the Rain, as we ſee our Rivers do; the <hi>Rhine</hi> and <hi>Danubius</hi> ſwell upon the diſſolution of Snow, and in much drought our Springs fail us, but thoſe are ſuch as materially depend upon the fall of Rain or Snow, and theſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſing the Springs alſo become dry, they being principally ordained by Nature for fertilizing and irrigating the Earth in its production of Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bage, Fruit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the benefit of Mankind; but ſuch are only Land-ſprings, and in no ſort to be called perpetual Springs, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the want of Rain or Snow for a long time are ſtill the ſame, and though great Rivers may almoſt be dried up, by a long and laſting diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance of wet, by the drineſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106707:24"/> of the ſuperficies of the Earth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibing it in its paſſage, for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of its drought, being <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ſicciſſimum,</hi> yet the heads of thoſe Rivers flow plentifully at the ſame time; ſo that another cauſality muſt be found out than Aerial ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies; and ſuppoſing there were (which ſome wittily contend for) certain commiſſures, chinks, and hollow veins in the Earth, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive much Rain that falls, yet what ſinks into thoſe clefts and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns bears no proportion at all with that plenty which hurries headlong into Rivers, and thence conveyed into the Sea, and conſequently ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry improbably propoſed to be in a manner the adaequate cauſation of laſting Springs, there being alſo ſubterrraneal generations, which for their production require alſo a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſupply of water. The ſecond opinion ſeems much leſs plauſible
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106707:24"/> than this, for if the cauſe be ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in the bowels of the Earth, then it either proceeds from Earth it ſelf changed into water, as <hi>Seneca,</hi> which being a thing againſt all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and experience, and back'd by no other authority than his own, needs no other confutation than pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion; or which is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, theſe Springs are made of Air pent up in the caverns of the Earth, and by the coldneſs thereof condenſed into water; this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, by Maſter <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s good leave, who here philoſophiſeth after his manner abſtruſely and metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, exceedeth all rational belief; for how is it imaginable, that there are ſo vaſt and ſo many empty ſpaces in the Earth as to contain ſo much Air for the making ſuch a quantity of water, and that in a moment, as ſprings daily out of the Earth; nay how can ſo much Air be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106707:25"/> as to furniſh ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of water, without exhauſting the whole ſtock, and conſequently make a <hi>Vacuum,</hi> not only <hi>diſſemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> which according to ſome is <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and natural, but alſo <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acervatum</hi> and <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to wit, ſuch as is totally repugnant to the fundamental Conſtitutions of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; this I ſay cannot be granted, eſpecially being that very many parts of Air ſerve for the making of one part of water containable in the ſame place, as Dr. <hi>French</hi> hath well obſerved; neither can any ſuch tranſmutation of Elements be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for though according to <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> water is convertible into va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, and the ſame vapours into water again, yet are theſe vapours nothing elſe but rarified water ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially, and Air will yield no more water that it contains vapours; but Air taking it purely of it ſelf, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106707:25"/> Air, is meerly Aetherial, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mixture at all, or the leaſt atoms of vapour, ſuch as is only above the Atmoſphere, and wholly unfit for reſpiration, or a <hi>pabulum,</hi> for ſuſtaining the flame of Life, which neceſſarily muſt have a Niter therein for that intent. The third opinion is moſt ancient and moſt true, being alſo a divine <hi>Epiphonema</hi> of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes, Omnia flumina intrant in mare, &amp; mare non redundat, ad locum unde exeunt flumina revertuntur ut iterum fluant.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">All Rivers, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> run into the Sea, and yet the Sea overflows not, into the place from whence the Rivers come, thither they return again.</q> Some one Man, deſirous to prove all Springs to be from Rain and Snow, puts a ſtrange gloſs upon this evident place of Scripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all Springs to have their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal from the Sea, and he tells us,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106707:26"/> that the queſtion is not about Rivers but Springs, and therefore <hi>Solomon</hi>'s aſſerting the Rivers to come from the Sea, makes out nothing for that of Springs; <hi>Quaſi verò;</hi> as if Rivers were not from Springs, and if Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, then by neceſſary conſequence Springs alſo are from the Sea. The ſame Aſſertor tells us alſo, that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſpeaks of the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea in great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, into which the Tide runs, they being near the Sea, which truely is but too great a ſtreſs put upon the Text; firſt, becauſe he tells us, that all Rivers, as well ſuch as admit of Ebbings and Flowings of the Sea as thoſe where no ſuch thing is, come from the Sea; and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it cannot be imagined that the whole bulk of water, which is running continually into the Sea, comes up again with the Tide, ſince the freſh is many Miles diſtant from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106707:26"/> the Tide, and no more of the River comes back again by tiding than what the Sea forc'd up at the time of its tiding, which ſhortly after at ebbing is again by the current of the River hurried back from whence it came. How then is it poſſible that the wiſeſt of Men ſhould poſitively affirm all Rivers to come from the Sea, ſince 'tis evident that the whole River can in no ſenſe be called the Tide, no more than the Tide can be called the whole River? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as venture thus to paraphraſe upon ſo plain Texts, muſt either conclude the Writers of the Holy Writ endowed only with natural ratiocination and not inſpiration, or which is as bad, they muſt admit in Divinity what's now in Phyſick, a legality or promiſcuous toleration as to Scriptures interpretation. But of this no more. Let us proceed now in proving the Seas ſole ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106707:27"/> of affording ſo great and laſting a ſupply of water for feeding of Springs. This Aſſertion certain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly is of a moſt indubitable truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being we ſee in almoſt innumerable places waters burſting out of the Earth, not after the manner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> boiling Fountains, but like vaſt im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petuous Rivers, which in no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability can be granted to ariſe ei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther from the condenſation of Air or Rain and Snow falling, or any ſuch like imaginary cauſation. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to make good the truth of this Hy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potheſis, by evidencing the manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how the Springs are at ſuch diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces deduceable from the Sea, even to the tops of higheſt Hills; <hi>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> labor hoc opus eſt.</hi> I imagin the only difficulty herein conſiſts (as I have ſaid) in this, that the adverſe party cannot conceive (granting the Sea to be lower than the tops of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains) how it ſhould, contrary to its
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106707:27"/> natural propenſion, be elevated to ſuch a height. For the better ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of which doubt, I will firſt tell you, that not only <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> but many ſolid Divines, hold that the Sea is as high if not higher than the higheſt Mountains, otherwiſe the Sea and Land make not up one global figure, and if ſo, the motion of the Sea to the tops of Hills is natural, and not at all beyond its level; but I go not about to defend this opinion. Granting therefore the Sea to be lower, I then argue thus, that 'tis not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to any that this Terreſtrial Body, eſpecially the bottom of the Sea, hath innumerable meatuſes, and is perforated with ſundry vora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginous inlets and patent mouths, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which and through which, as ſo many hydragogical channels, water may freely paſs, otherwiſe why do winds proceed more apparently,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106707:28"/> and after a more violent manner from the Sea than from the Land they being cauſed by the eruption of exhalations from thoſe fiſſures in the bottom of the Sea: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted, 'tis no hard matter to allow the afflux and reflux of the Sea preſſing the other water with their exceeding great weight, to exalt the ſame through thoſe ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raneal channels even to the tops of higheſt Mountains; for the water being thus preſſed with the adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious acceſs of water, either drawn thither by the Moon, or cauſed as ſome think by the Earths motion, muſt needs force it ſelf downward ſpontaneouſly; and finding thoſe patent paſſages, is (as I may well ſay) thruſt into thoſe <hi>hydrophalacia</hi> of the higheſt Mountains, where ſeeking out an <hi>exit,</hi> being thus bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with weight, burſts forth into Springs and Rivers. If it ſhould
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106707:28"/> be objected, that the flux of the Sea and Tides are ſpent in their courſe into Rivers; I anſwer, that theſe ſubterranean caverns will be firſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as being more immediately under the weight, and what is to ſpare only runs into Rivers, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing natural to all heavy bodies, even having no force put upon them, to deſcend perpendicularly, rather than in an oblique line. Others may ſay, that if the flux of the Sea, or weight of accumulated waters, ſhould cauſe Springs, then would our Springs ceaſe running when the Tide or flux of waters is out from our parts, and ſo the like of other parts of the world; to which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that the Sea ebbs and flows every twelve hours over the face of the world where ever any ſuch reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procation is, and therefore little or no time is left for ſuch a ſurceaſe of weight, as to alter the current of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106707:29"/> Springs, and not only thoſe that have the ſame Meridian as <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Dunbar,</hi> though ſome Degrees different in Latitude, have every twelve hours full Sea at the ſame time, but alſo ſuch as have a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Meridian, and not the ſame in Longitude, have notwithſtanding the ſame returns as to ſpace of time, though not at the ſame time. If any Seas be without theſe Tides, as the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea is ſaid to be, its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo near the Northern Pole, and ſome part thereof within the Artick Circle, where the Air is thick and groſs, may ſupply the want of Tides as to Springs. Which that I may make good, and thereby anſwer all other imaginable doubts and objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt this aſſertion, I ſhall take occaſion of producing a ſecond reaſon perſwading to this original, <hi>viz.</hi> the mighty Tempeſts and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binious Winds, the deſcent of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106707:29"/> and chiefly the incumbency of the Air it ſelf, by all which the water is both preſſed and expreſſed; and for further manifeſtation hereof, give me leave to illuſtrate as a moſt convincing argument, the great weight of Air upon this terraqueous Globe, which is apparently made out by <hi>Torricellius</hi> his Experiment in a Veſſel of Quickſilver, inſtanced by that truely Noble and Illuſtrious Gentleman Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> thus: <q rend="margQuotes">Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving prepared a Glaſs Tube, and ſtopped up one of its extremities with a Seal hermetical, fill it with Quickſilver, and ſtop the other extream with your middle finger, then having inverted the Tube, immerge the extream ſtopt by your finger into a Veſſel filled with Quickſilver, not withdrawing your finger until the end of the Tube be at leaſt three or four Inches deep in the ſubjacent Quickſilver,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106707:30"/> for ſo you prevent all inſinuation of Air. This done, and the Tube fixed in a perpendicular poſition, upon the ſubduction of your finger from the lower orifice, you may obſerve almoſt half the Quickſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver contained in the Tube to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend ſpeedily into the reſtagnant or ſubjacent Quickſilver, leaving almoſt half of the ſuperiour part of the Tube, according to all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, at leaſt void and empty. Now place this Veſſel thus fitted upon the top of an high Hill, for example, where the Air is leſs weighty and incumbent than at the bottom of the Hill, and you ſhall perceive the Quickſilver in the Tube to deſcend, and that in the Veſſel made higher; whereas if you remove the Veſſel to the bottom of the Hill, where the Air is groſſer and more incumbent, that Quickſilver in the Tube will
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106707:30"/> aſcend, and the other in the Veſſel deſcend; ſo that the variety of places where the Air is various, makes a variety of motion higher or lower in the Quickſilver, which cannot be from any other cauſe than the different gravity of Air in different places; for the Air of its own nature is heavy, and can be ſaid to be light only comparitively, or as it is leſs ponderous than Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Earth, nor can there be given any more manifeſt reaſons for the Airs tendency upward from the convexity of the Earth than this, that being in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree ponderous in all its particles, theſe deſcend from the upper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Atmoſphere, and bear upon and mutually compel each other until they beat upon the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Earth, and are by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſolidity thereof reper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed up again to ſome diſtance,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106707:31"/> ſo that the motion of the Air up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is properly a reſilition not natural but violent.</q>Now whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this gravity be congenial and inherent in the Air, or whether it be cauſed by a conformity to the magnetick attraction of the Earth, matters not at all as to our preſent purpoſe, being we have a depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion amongſt the particles of the Air, in their tendency from the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſphere down to the ſurface of our Globe, and the diameter of the Sphere of Air being much larger than that of the terraqueous Globe, we have thereupon from the convex to the concave thereof a compreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing weight upon the ſurface of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters equivalent to that upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtagnant Liquor in the foreſaid Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. I ſhall further urge ſome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments <hi>de facto,</hi> and tell you, that <hi>Pliny</hi> writes of a Spring which pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually obſerves the Seas motion in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106707:31"/> its ebbing and flowing. <hi>Antonius Vaſconzello,</hi> a Father of the Society, in his Deſcription of <hi>Portugal,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions a ſtrange and remarkable Lake on the top of the Mountain <hi>Ermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> whoſe nature is, ſaith he, <hi>ut aeſtuante oceano &amp; ipſe pariter aeſtuans ſit lacus,</hi> that is, punctually to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Seas reciprocation, even as to its raging more or leſs with fourges; <hi>luculentum ſanè</hi> (ſaith <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher) occulti cum oceano per hydragogos canales correſponſus ſignum,</hi> an evident ſign of the ſubterraneal correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence this Lake hath with the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean through hydragogical convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances and caverns. And learned <hi>Kircher</hi> alſo aſſures us hereof when he ſaith, <hi>Aliqui fontes fluxum &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxum maris aemulantur,</hi> and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, relates a lepid ſtory of a Fountain, or rather a River in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia,</hi> in a ſabulous Plain, breaking out with the Tides twice every na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106707:32"/> day, with ſuch a violent force and noiſe (whence 'tis called <hi>Boller<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum</hi>) that it overflows all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of that Valley, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing after the ſame manner as it increaſed, at laſt hides it ſelf totally in its head. Biſhop <hi>Theodorus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in media hujus ſuperficie menſam opiparè lautéque conſtruxit, &amp;c.</hi> made a moſt magnificent Banquet in the middle of this Valley, and thither invited and brought with him di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Ladies, when on the ſudden the River burſting forth, whilſt they careſſed Nature and made merry, did ſo wet them, even more than mid-way up, that they were forced to wade out, when as thoſe that were conſcious to the deſign, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew themſelves by time, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently derided the poor Females infortunity. <hi>Interdum ſeria ludis, &amp; è contra.</hi> And thus much, as far as we poor haggard Mortals can
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106707:32"/> reach by the Light of Nature, being Moles rather than Men ever ſince our firſt Fall, whoſe weak and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Opticks lead us only to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of the exteriour and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious parts of Nature, not perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious enough to penetrate her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour and abſtruſe excellencies; nor can we ſpeculate, faith Doctor <hi>Charleton,</hi> her glorious beauty in the direct and incident Line of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences and formal Cauſes, but in that reflected and refracted one of Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, nor that neither, without ſo much of obſcurity as leaves an incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in our apprehenſions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains our ambition of an Apodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Science, to the darkſom Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of meerly conjectural Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. If therefore I have erected any veriſimilous conjecture concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the cauſation of Springs, and their derivation from their proper Originals, and given but any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106707:33"/> Solution of that abſtruſe Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenon, I hope others as well as my ſelf will reſt contented.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the true Eſſence and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuent Principles of Vitriol.</head>
               <p>GReat, pregnant, and teeming Conſtitutions, and ſuch as are conſtellated unto knowledge, think they come ſhort of themſelves, if they outgo not others; and indeed they may well think they do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, 'till they outdo all. But my <hi>Minerva</hi> bids me ſay, <hi>Nos numeri ſumus,</hi> and I ſhall think I have done well, if in the diſquiſition of the true nature of Vitriol, I hold the ſtirrop to Pyrotechnical Philoſophy, and ſo urge nothing, but what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toptical
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106707:33"/> experience, reaſon and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, ſhall illuſtrate. Firſt then, I define<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Vitriol to be a Mineral Body, generated in the Bowels of the Earth from a ſulphureous Spirit, Water, and the Mineral either of Iron or Copper, or both; and that theſe are the material Ingredients of its compoſition appears from hence, becauſe its acidity and cauſtical acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony it neceſſarily hath from the Spirit of Sulphur, its clarity and fluidity from Water, and its colour and metalline taſte either from the Mineral of Copper or Iron; and of theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi> Spirit of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, Water, and an Ironiſh or Copper Glebe, is Vitriol compoſed, which is alſo called <hi>Atramentum Sutorium,</hi> and by the <hi>Greeks</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Some notwithſtanding will have it compoſed of Allum and Sulphur, becauſe, ſay they, take a Vitrioline Loam or Clay, and dilute it with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106707:34"/> water, and upon ſtanding in a cold Cellar you may gather thence an alluminous Effloreſcence; to which I yield ſo far, as that there may be a mixture of Allum with Vitriol, in regard of their affinity, but it follows not thereupon, that Allum makes up its compoſition of parts; for though as all other Minerals have their acidity from Spirit of Sulphur, and are both under that general notion of Salt and Concrete Juyces, yet cannot they, Vitriol eſpecially, be called purely and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Salts, but make up ſpecifick differences of <hi>ſuch</hi> Salts. Others deny Sulphur to be an ingredient, becauſe in the calcination of Vitriol there's no ſmell of Sulphur, as is when Antimony, Orpin, or Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſites, are calcin'd, though theſe be far more compact ſolid Bodies; but the reaſon of this is, becauſe it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes only of the Spirit and more
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106707:34"/> ſubtil parts of Sulphur, the others of the groſſer ſubſtance. Now to ſhew you how Vitriol becomes a ſpecifick Salt, I muſt firſt premiſe this general Hypotheſis, that there is a common Salt of Nature, and Water, which diffuſe themſelves throughout all the particles of this Geocoſm, and being conſidered in themſelves, are indifferent Subjects for the reception of various forms, accordingly as they meet with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Glebes in the bowels of the Earth; therefore when Water impregnated with Spirit of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, or a Vapour from that accen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Body of Sulphur, paſſeth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough a ſalſuginous Glebe, already endowed with the common Salt of Nature, it produceth Salt, when thorough nitrous Veins Niter, when thorough alluminous Allum, when thorough a Copperas white Vitriol, when thorough a Silver Mine blew
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106707:35"/> Vitriol, and laſtly when thorough an Ironiſh Glebe it ſhares of ſome particles of Iron (more or leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proportion of the Waters acidity and the fertility of the Vein) and produceth green Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol. So that if Water be thus tinged with this acid Spirit, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the true and proper <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum</hi> for the diſſolving of all ſorts of Glebes whatſoever, and this Liquor thus repleniſh'd, <hi>v. g.</hi> with the raments of Iron, is condenſed into this Vitriol which now I ſpeak of. And that I may further declare ſome genuine Effects of this Vitriol, I ſay that 'tis cauſtical, and eateth into and corrupts all ſorts of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, excepting Lead, which it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not penetrate by reaſon of its Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curial parts, which reſiſteth and repreſſeth its activity. But to ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize it more intrinſically, this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol conſiſting of the aforeſaid three
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106707:35"/> ſuſtances yieldeth ſpagyrically ſeven ſeveral Medicaments; firſt, there is extracted from it <hi>per Balneum vapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſum</hi> Water, which is called <hi>Ros Vitrioli,</hi> becauſe of its Aerial light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and partakes leaſt of all of the Spirit of Sulphur; this corroborates the Bowels, mitigates the inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Blood, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the Brain with its heat and ſiccity. Secondly, there's another Water drawn <hi>per arenam,</hi> and this partakes more of the Spirit of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, and is called the ſecond Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Vitriol; it purgeth the Reins, opens obſtructions in the paſſage of Urine, and helpeth all internal cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſions, if taken in Veal Broath faſting. Thirdly, there's extracted another ſubſtance of Vitriol, which is the moſt ſubtil portion of Sulphur, and called the Spirit of Vitriol, a moſt admirable <hi>Prophylacticon</hi> or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative againſt all ſorts of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106707:36"/> for whatever it finds in the Body putredinous, poyſonous, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently diſpoſed to any capital Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, it preſently incides, attenuates, and waſtes, it purifies the Blood from all fuliginous damps, prevents the Stone, purgeth the Reins and Bladder, conſuming all mucilaginous and tartarous viſcoſity whatever. Fourthly, being tortur'd with a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther degree of Fire it gives a certain Oyl, not ſo ſafe to be taken inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though ſome, by reaſon that it's a Narcotick, uſe it in Maniacal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers; but outwardly it is uſed for curing Impoſthumes. Fifthly, a certain Vitriol is brought over the Helm, which Chymiſts call <hi>Purificatum</hi> or <hi>Sal Vitrioli,</hi> being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the remaining Dregs from the acid Spirit, repreſenting a purpliſh thin Earth, and good externally uſed as aforeſaid; this is not <hi>Sal Vitrioli Vomitivi</hi> ſo much uſed at
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106707:36"/> preſent, being a repeated Solution of white Vitriol, with frequent filtrations. Sixthly, all the Spirits being drawn off, there remains a certain Aerial ſubſtance, being a moſt ſubtil duſt of Vitriol, which may be called <hi>Ferrum</hi> or <hi>Aes Vitrioli,</hi> being it may be reduced into either of them; this cleanſeth rotten Sores, and is an Incarnative. And ſeventhly and laſtly, all Diſtillation ended, there remains in the bottom of the Retort or Reverberatory a <hi>Caput mortuum</hi> or Colcotar, or <hi>Terra Vitrioli,</hi> and inſervient for mixing with cicatrizing Plaiſters.</p>
               <p>Thus have I, to my weak ability, analyzed the whole Body of Vitriol; <hi>In quod quid reſolvi poteſt, ex illo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſario debet conſtare.</hi> But before I advance further in my journy home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, I will inſtance only in one proceſs of making artificial Vitriol, for the better clearing and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106707:37"/> the nativity of natural Vitriol, which Dr. <hi>Browne,</hi> as an Eye-witneſs, ſaith in <hi>Hungary</hi> to be thus: <q rend="margQuotes">There is (ſaith he) a Vitriol Mine nigh the Golden Mine, the Earth or Ore whereof is reddiſh, and ſometimes greeniſh, infuſe this Earth in water three days, then poure off the water, and boil it ſeven days in a leaden Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, 'till it comes to a thick gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulated whitiſh or greeniſh ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, according as the Ore is either of Braſs or Iron, and this is then pure Vitriol, and being reduced to a Calx in an Oven ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to make <hi>Aqua fortis.</hi>
                  </q> But there is beſides the Ore or Glebe of Vitriol, a natural cryſtallized Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol in a Mine in <hi>Paradiſe-Hill</hi> in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and the ſame Doctor was conducted by a Mine-man at <hi>Schem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitz</hi> under ground, 'till he came where he ſhewed him great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106707:37"/> of natural Vitriol, it ſhooting upon the ſtones and earth, upon the floor and ſides of the paſſages, as it doth by Art in the pans and about the ſticks, not hanging from the top, as ordinarily it doth, like Iſicles. The Principles and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of Vitriol being thus cleared, I ſhall now only evidence the great affinity betwixt Iron and Copper, and conſequently betwixt the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triols of them both, and if you pleaſe of their Effects alſo, and this not only as much conduceable to my preſent purpoſe, as for the oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that receiv'd Opinion of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, which admits no tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Metal. This aforeſaid lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Traveller writes of two Vitriol waters in the Copper Mine of <hi>Heron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grundt,</hi> which turns Iron into Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; theſe Springs lye very deep in the Mine, and the moſt uſeleſs old Iron is hereby turned into the pureſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106707:38"/> Copper; the Iron being left therein about fourteen days is rendred more ductil, malleable, and eaſily melted Copper than any other. The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous, becauſe univerſally lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Kircher,</hi> and other ſound Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts, will not have this to be a tranſmutation of one Metal into another, and their reaſon is, becauſe this water ſaturated with a <hi>Vitriolum Veneris,</hi> and meeting with ſuch a Body, ſo ready to receive it as <hi>Mars,</hi> it depoſeth <hi>Venus,</hi> who immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſinuates her ſelf ſo far into <hi>Mars,</hi> that ſhe doth <hi>dividere</hi> and <hi>imperare,</hi> and at laſt ſubſtitutes her own Body, and precipitates that of <hi>Mars.</hi> But Dr. <hi>Browne</hi> averreth, that though in the changing of Iron into Copper in theſe Springs, many parts are precipitated and lye at the bottom in powder, yet theſe parts, ſaith he, are not Iron but Copper, for that he took of this powder out
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106707:38"/> of the Spring and melted it into excellent Copper, ſo that if the Iron be not totally changed into Copper, God knows what becomes on it. If this be ſo, (and we have no reaſon to think the contrary) why Art, in the imitation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may not make the ſame tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation I know not, and then welcome to Town the Philoſophers Stone. I am ſure I ſaw in the Grand Duke of <hi>Florence</hi> his Gallery of Rarities, a Horſe-ſhooe, half Gold half Iron, that part which is now Gold having been formerly Iron, as the univerſally received tradition of that place aſſerteth. But this is not all, for the ſame Doctor ſaith, he drank out of an handſom Cup made out of this ſort of Copper, which formerly was Iron, and gilt all over, and had a piece of Silver Ore faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the middle of it, with this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription graved on the outſide.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:106707:39"/>
                  <l>Eiſen were ich, kupſer bin ich,</l>
                  <l>Silver trag ich, goldt bedeckt mich.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Copper I am, but Iron was of old;</l>
                  <l>Silver I carry, covered am with Gold.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>I would willingly beg pardon, and expatiate a little further into this large field of Phyſiology, and ſay ſomething of the Seeds of Petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, or lapidifical Principle, which converts all Materials it meets withall into a ſtony concrete; but I ſhall only hint at ſome one preſident, with the definition of the thing it ſelf; whereby you may be more confirmed in that opinion of a corporeal tranſmutation of of Subſtances. <hi>Succus lapidificus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Kircher) nil aliud eſt quam humor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibilium corpuſculorum ex lapidoſis veris nitroſis ſaliniſque locis abraſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum miſturá conſtitutus elaboratuſque;</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:106707:39"/> and theſe <hi>corpuſcula</hi> being perfectly mixed together and united, make up this <hi>Succus lapidificus,</hi> or humour, and being they have a natural ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of reduction to their own for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtate and condition, hence is it, that through their ſpirituous Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they penetrate the moſt abſtruſe and moſt minute fibrous particles of whatever convertible Body they meet withall, and by their acrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious acidity conſume, and as it were eat up their ſofter parts prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, and in their place ſubſtitute themſelves, by means whereof they imbody themſelves into a ſtony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. This definition thus evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced, is made good by a <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſto</hi> from the forenamed Doctor: <q rend="margQuotes">For (ſaith he) the hot Bath of <hi>Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenbach</hi> petrefieth, ſo as thoſe Trees with which they built the ſides of the Bath, next above the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are entirely turned into Stone,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106707:40"/> and it's not unpleaſant to obſerve, how Nature doth here aſſiſt Art, and out of the Body of a Fir frames a moſt ſtately Column of of Stone. I will end this Chapter</q> with a remarkable piece of Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe this Doctor had at <hi>Buda,</hi> the digreſſion I hope is pardonable. One <hi>Mortizan Ephendi,</hi> (a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Perſon of Note, and who had been Envoy Extraordinary with our Emperour at <hi>Vienna</hi>) treated this Doctor very kindly, and amongſt other diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes asked him what was the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Name, and after he had told him his Name was <hi>Michael Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowitski,</hi> his Reply was, <hi>What?</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael, <hi>that's a good Name, that's the Name of the greateſt Saint in Heaven, excepting</hi> Mary. An Expreſſion I muſt confeſs no leſs admirable in a <hi>Turk,</hi> than commendable in a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:106707:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. Of our Vitrioline Spaw at <hi>Durham.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Confeſs I have even ſhipwrackt your patience, and kept you out too long at Sea. If I have been your faithful Pilot, ſo far as to land you at the ſafe harbour of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Truth, I have much more than I can deſerve, and as much indeed as I can deſire; eſpecially ſince our Voyage hath been full of difficulties, which have caſt us upon thoſe inevitable Rocks of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certitude and obſcurity; but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, though I have been through thoſe Foggs and Miſts of various Opinions ſo benighted, that I dare not be magiſterial in any of my
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106707:41"/> Phyſiological Diſquiſitions, yet I can boldly take the confidence to wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you to <hi>Durham,</hi> where you ſhall find the entertainment of a moſt delightful Field, raiſed and heightened almoſt round from its adjacent continents, ventilated with a moſt ſweet and open Air, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated naturally with convenient Walks, and neighboured with an uſeful Wood. Out of the midſt hereof riſeth this our wholeſom and plentiful Spring, which as it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richeth our Inhabitants with an ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable Treaſure of Health, ſo will it compenſate the pains of Foreigners in order to the ſame. And that I may the better evidence the truth hereof, and come directly to the proſecution of our main Deſign, I will draw a Map or Scheme of the Heads of our intended Enquiries, that ſo we may prepare the Minds of our Readers to accompany us
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106707:41"/> more ſmoothly and eaſily to a right underſtanding of what we intend to prove. Firſt then, let me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, what is wanting in this our Vitrioline Spaw to make up the true Body of Vitriol, and compleat its definition expreſly laid down in the foregoing Chapter? That it hath Water in a moſt plentiful current is evident, that it hath alſo a Spirit of Sulphur is apparent from the acid taſte thereof, for nothing can make this taſte in Minerals but Spirit of Sulphur, as the renowned <hi>Kircher</hi> expreſly manifeſteth in theſe words, <hi>Baſis unica &amp; abſoluta origo omnium aciditatum Mineralium eſt à Spiritu Sulphuris acido;</hi> neither need we much doubt of Sulphur and its va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porous Spirit where we have ſo much Coal. The only doubt then will be, whether this our Water thus impregnated with acidity hath in it a Mineral Glebe of Iron or not?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106707:42"/> And that this may clearly appear, I firſt call in the Senſes of Smelling and Taſting to atteſt, it having both a Vitrioline or Ironiſh taſte and odour. Secondly, let our own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments witneſs the ſame, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſtilled it, both after the manner expreſſed in the former Chapter and by Retort <hi>ex arena,</hi> from a Pottle thereof there remained in the bottom a ruſty Iron-like pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in quantity about ten grains, which in taſte had a piercing ſharp Vitrioline pungency, ſomewhat harſh. After diſtillation I tryed it by coction, 'till a third part was conſumed, the remainder I let ſettle for three days, that the <hi>contentum</hi> might be the better ſeparated, and the ſediment was the very ſame as formerly. Indeed by evaporation I had much leſs ſediment remaining, which makes me more than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably conjecture, that it is impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106707:42"/> not ſo much with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal ſubſtance as with the ſpiritual and ſubtil particles of the ſaid Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol; for the Water being acuated with a ſulphureous acidity, and paſſing ſwiftly through ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Vein of Iron, corrodes lightly its more tenuous and Aerial parts, reſolving them ſo, as the Water imbibes in a manner only the vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Atoms, with which it becomes thus ſaturated; I ſay volatile, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though diſtilled in a Glaſs Still and luted hermetically, yet are the Spirits ſooner ſublimed than the Water, and take wing ſo ſwiftly, that before any Water come over they are unbodied and evaporated, no odour nor taſte at all remaining in the Water, neither will it then become any otherwiſe tinged with Gall than common Spring-water, though before diſtillation, with the mixture of two or three grains of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106707:43"/> the powder of Galls, an ordinary Glaſs full becomes as purpureouſly red as our genuine and beſt coloured Claret. And hereupon I now come to my third Argument, deſumed from the tincture it hath from the powder of Galls, and truly this is a work eaſily performed upon one legg, notwithſtanding a Gyant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>objection, or rather Aſſertion, of a learned, induſtrious, and Pyrotech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Phyſitian, to the contrary. I remember the <hi>Hyperaſpiſtes</hi> of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough-Spaw</hi> is highly charged with a <hi>Non ſequitur,</hi> in ſaying, a ſmall quantity of Gall being put into the Spaw-water doth turn into a dark coloured Claret, <hi>Ergò,</hi> there is Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol in it. I hope I have no great guilt in intermedling with others Affairs, having, God knows, but but too much to mind at home, but when Juſtice, Truth, and my own preſent Concern command, I muſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106707:43"/> though with reluctancy affirm, that his <hi>Ergò</hi> ſtands good, and if the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnt Allum-ſtone Experiment be the ſame with that his Antagoniſt relates of Coal, they neither will hold water, I mean tinctur'd water. For having followed his own di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, I took a pretty quantity of Coal, powder'd it, added Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, ſharpened with Spirit of Sulphur for its diſſolution, filter'd it 'till 'twas clear, then put pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Gall thereto, and what thence was the reſult? truely the adding of the Gall added no more change as to colour, than what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gall was added, that is, the water both before and after had a dark dusky colour, ſuch as is the natural tincture of all Coal, and that was all. Let not my good Friend ſay, (which was his Anſwer to the <hi>Scarborough-Buckler</hi>) that I made only an infuſion, and no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106707:44"/> for I ſharpened the water to divers degrees for its more intim penetration and diſſolution. I am confident this conſcientious good Man grounded this poſition upon ſome imaginary probability, no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toptical atteſtation, but I ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him better preſently. I have made no tryal of the tincture from unburt Allum-ſtone, but I dare aver, that if it tingeth upon the mixture with Gall, 'tis <hi>quatenus</hi> there's Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol mixed therewith, there being ſuch an analogical agreement 'twixt Allum and Vitriol, both as to ſenſe and ſenſible operations, that 'tis no hard matter to admit of a combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, they being both under the <hi>genus</hi> of ſaline concrete Juyces, and whether ſo differenced as to make a diſtinct <hi>ſpecies</hi> of Salt I ſhall not here endeavour to determin; eſpecially ſince <hi>Kircher</hi> affirms from experience, <hi>in vitriolo alumen conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106707:44"/> luto enim ejus aqua diluto, alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ex eo effloreſcit;</hi> and if in Vitriol Allum, why not in Allum Vitriol? The ſame alſo may be ſaid of Coal (to make good my late promiſe to my Friend) that, it may be, all Coal is not alike, ſome without, and ſome with an intermixture of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, diſſeminated and interſperſed amongſt its ſulphureous Veins, and therefore it may be our good Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Experiment light ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually of a Coal thus vitriolated, but then we muſt not conclude the Coal, but the Vitriol in the Coal, to give the tincture with Gall. And that this my precarious <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> may have ſome Pillar to lean upon, I muſt confeſs I have ſeen much, and have divers pieces of a Mineral Marchaſite or <hi>Pyrites,</hi> in which, though doubtleſs there be much Sulphur, as appears by its ſcintil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and odour, the powder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106707:45"/> being caſt into the fire, as alſo from its unctuoſity upon diſtillation; yet may this be only the embrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Sulphur of Copper or Iron, and the acid water paſſing through the Coal Mine interſperſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, licks up only ſome corpuſcles of the Metalline parts of this Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſite in its paſſage, as being its deſired <hi>Alkali,</hi> and being impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated herewith, renders it ſelf thus inriched for our uſe; neither can it be rationally ſaid, that the Sulphur is likewiſe imbibed, for being an unctuous and inflammable ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in the <hi>compoſitum,</hi> it reſiſts the activity of the acid Vehicle, as is manifeſt from the very Eſſence of Sulphur, out of which is made an Oyntment for preſerving Cables and ſuch like from corroſion, and makes them live, (ſpeaking meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically,) in the water everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly. But admit this water
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106707:45"/> ſhould participate of the Sulphur, is it therefore to be rejected? 'Pray how many wholſom Preparations of Sulphur are taken inwardly and ſucceſsfully in Phthyſical Diſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? But however it be, as to this, here we certainly have a Vitriol yielding a proper tincture upon the acceſs of Gall, which is all I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for. I will yet argue further for this our Vitrioline Spaw. Let any one drink Vitrioline of Iron diſſolved in water, and he ſhall ſee his Excrements tinctur'd either black or greeniſh, from the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation of the Vitriol by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Alkali,</hi> and the very ſame effect is produced by drinking of this our <hi>Spaw:</hi> This cannot be from the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol of Copper, becauſe this Metal makes white Vitriol, not green as Iron doth, neither will any ſay we have any Copper Mine, as we have Iron, in theſe parts. Moreover,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106707:46"/> write what you pleaſe with the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ferrugineous Vitriol, and after it is dry there ſhall nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, but beſmear what is written with a ſimple Infuſion of Gall, and in a moment the <hi>Alkali</hi> of the Gall makes the Letters black; and again by any potent acidity, as <hi>v. g. Aqua fortis,</hi> they are quite deleted; and yet again by any fixt <hi>Alkali,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come black as before: By which foundation of Cryptography 'tis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, not only that the acidity of Vitriol tingeth not black, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it be imbibed and abſumpted with an <hi>Alkali,</hi> but alſo that no <hi>Alkali</hi> tingeth black without a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trioline acidity. This my poſitive Aſſertion is ſufficiently back'd by that inquiſitive Chymiſt and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Philoſopher <hi>Ot. Tachenius,</hi> who after much pains taken in this Diſquiſition concludes thus: <hi>Unde liquet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quod Sal volatile vel
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106707:46"/> Alkali gallarum vel corticum granato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vel herbarum vulnerariarum, non tingunt colore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nigro, niſi cum ferro in minerali acido ſoluto.</hi> But why is not our Urine tinged black as well as the Excrements? This I ſay is becauſe the Colcothar is precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the Liquor comes into the Miſeraicks, ſo as it neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the Guts. <hi>Cyprus</hi> Vitriol indeed, being much from Copper, turns black with Galls, but this is by reaſon of its intermixture with Iron, for <hi>Vitriolum Veneris</hi> purely without <hi>Mars</hi> turns not black with Galls, as that of <hi>Mars</hi> without <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> will, though they being as Man and Wife joyned together, cannot well be found the one without ſome mixture of the other. White Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol of <hi>Corinth</hi> partakes of both, but more of <hi>Venus,</hi> for which cauſe, as being alſo not enriched much with the <hi>Acidum naturale,</hi> it ſlowly
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106707:47"/> becomes black with Galls. But <hi>Roman</hi> Vitriol, which partakes moſt of Iron, preſently tingeth black; ſo doth artificial Vitriol that is made of the ſhavings of Steel and Spirit of Vitriol, the Vitriol corrodes and reſolves the ſhavings and becomes ſweet; and hence it is indeed, that all chalybiate Medicines are ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful in all cochectical and obſtinate Diſeaſes, the <hi>Alkali</hi> of the Steel im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibing the acidity and ſowreneſs of the Blood, and conſequently dulci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the ſame. And this is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal reaſon our <hi>Spaw,</hi> being impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with Vitriol of Iron, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth ſuch rare effects. If it be demanded, why theſe ferruginous or vitrioline acid Fountains make not the Tongue and Mouth black, as it doth the Excrements? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that this happens, becauſe the acid Spirit, mixed with the water, corroding the immature
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106707:47"/> Vein of Iron, or whilſt it is <hi>in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiis ſolutis,</hi> is not as yet ſaturated, we drinking it whilſt it is in the very action of corroſion, and hath not yet time to precipitate in the Tongue, but ſo ſoon as this grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acidity is ſnatched into the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, the Colcothar being preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated gives the tincture, the aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity being then perfectly coagulated with its <hi>Alkali,</hi> and whatever mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilaginous matter it meets withall in that coagulation, it turns all into its own nature of conſtriction, as we may ſee in the nativity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of that <hi>Herculean</hi> Diſeaſe the Stone, and this <hi>coagulum</hi> is that which ordinarily Phyſitians call <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilation</hi> or Obſtruction, a noted hard word amongſt our Water-caſters, thoſe pedantick Pretenders to Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who if they can but ſhake an Urinal, and gravely tell you of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and obſtructions, or that the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106707:48"/> 
                  <hi>Archeus</hi> is inraged, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wiſe enough to rival <hi>Solomon,</hi> when indeed they are as truely ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the original of thoſe words as their deluded Patients, who even gape with admiration of their profound Phyſiology. But to return home from the country, this our water is therefore to be drunk at the Fountain-head, for if it be let ſtand and ſettle any long time, the action, and conſequently the benefit and virtue ceaſeth, the acid Spirit being imbibed and drunk up by the immature Iron or Vitriol thereof, enfeebled and diſarmed of its acidity, and together with the reſolved Mineral is precipitated into Oker, which lyes at the bottom in a yellowiſh, not a black colour, as it is ſeen in all Vitrioline <hi>Spaws,</hi> it having then no other proper <hi>Alkali</hi> that it meets withall, as it doth in the Stomach or elſewhere, to cauſe a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106707:48"/> blackiſh precipitation; neither is its acidity ſo diſarmed by the corroſion of the Iron Vein, that it quite lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth its reſolving and coagulating force, with other <hi>Alkalies</hi> in the Stomach, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the acidity is yet predominant, and after it hath ſpent part of its virtue upon the Iron raments, there is yet ſufficient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining for reſolution and coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation elſewhere, accordingly as it ſhall meet with other <hi>Alkalies</hi> for that purpoſe; for if this were not ſo, we ſhould not have that acidity which ſenſibly we perceive and taſte in this water, and then <hi>divites dimittuntur manes.</hi> Beſides this ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phureous acidity in the water, there are unſpecificated acids in the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of our Body, which run headlong with a natural propenſity to the Vitriol or Eſurine Salt of Iron, and therewith coagulated and ejected, together with the obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106707:49"/> humours, upon a ſtrong irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Nature to expel her Ironiſh Enemy, and upon this account it is, that Iron and Steel, or rather their Vitriol, are ſaid to open Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions. I would not have any think, that becauſe Nature riſeth in arms againſt all that's offenſive, as Iron is, and endeavours its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, that therefore Purgatives are not convenient, for even then are they moſt fitting, when the coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation after fermentation is moſt prevalent; Nature can but do her utmoſt endeavour, and when that is not ſufficient, then the Phyſitian takes up the Cudgels for her aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. And here, to rectifie the miſapprehenſions of ſome, I muſt beg pardon to tell them, that what Purgatives we adminiſter work not by attraction or election (unleſs we of that freedom to Druggs which ſome deny to our ſelves) but by irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106707:49"/> in the <hi>primis viis</hi> and Bowels, and by fermentation in the Blood and Humours, and this purgative power by irritation depends not of the five Principles, Salt, Sulphur, Water, Earth, and Spirits, <hi>disjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctim</hi> and ſingly, but of moſt or all of them <hi>conjunctim,</hi> though I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the fermentation is almoſt only from the Salts. I fear I have ſpoken Aenigmatically and in the dark to ſomes underſtanding, in ſo often repeating the word <hi>Alkali,</hi> I will therefore briefly explain the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy and ſignification thereof. By <hi>Alkali</hi> therefore, or <hi>Sal Alkali,</hi> is meant all ſuch Salts as mortifie whatſoever acidities they meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, not only in the Vegitable, but alſo in the Animal and Mineral Kingdom; I ſay, whatſoever im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibes or ſucks up the acid Salts, and conſequently ſweetens the Blood and Humours, is called by the name
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106707:50"/> of <hi>Alkali,</hi> whether it be a fixt Salt or volatile, manifeſt or occult. This <hi>Alkali</hi> is made of the Herb <hi>Kali,</hi> brought to us out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> being there burnt into aſhes, and ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported: Some call it <hi>Soda,</hi> others <hi>Alumen catinum,</hi> but properly 'tis called <hi>Sal Kali</hi> or <hi>Alkali.</hi> I will now haſten to ſpeak of the Virtues of this our <hi>Spaw,</hi> which indeed was my main Deſign propoſed in this trifling Treatiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:106707:50"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. Of the Virtues of this Spaw.</head>
               <p>I Muſt confeſs the ſubtil and pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating Spirit, called by <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus</hi> his <hi>Arcanum,</hi> and by <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont primum ens Salium, Spiritus eſuriens,</hi> by <hi>Paracelſus Sal circulatum,</hi> which indeed is his <hi>Albaheſt</hi> or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal embrionative Solvent; this Spirit I ſay cannot be extracted out of this water, neither can it ſcarce be found in its pure ſpirituality, but as infolded and lock'd up in the arms of ſome Mineral after coagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, yet by a skilful Artiſt it may be extracted out of the <hi>totum mixtum</hi> or entire Body of Vitriol, without being any way corroſive at all. And with this Spirit it is, that our <hi>Spaw</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:106707:51"/> hath its great affinity, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently its excellency, penetrating by its tenuity of parts the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and ſecluſe parts of our Bodies. This being premiſed, 'twill be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to every ones capacity, to know and acknowledge the great advantages which are accrued, as well for preventing as curing moſt ſtubborn and laſting Diſeaſes. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever for the better ſatisfaction, of the Vulgar principally, I ſhall briefly ſay ſomething in general, and not omit in particular what autoptical Obſervations I have made theſe two or three laſt Summers by-paſt. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the precedent Chapter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly demonſtrated the manifold Operations of Vitriol, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently not a few of this our <hi>Spaw,</hi> my Province now will be of an eaſie charge, and therefore I will briefly acquaint you, that the firſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of this water, <hi>quatenus</hi> water,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106707:51"/> actually moiſtens and cools, but as it is befriended with a Mineral mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it heats and drys, ſo that it becomes hereby effectually preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for the accompliſhing of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent indications, and reducing even contrary Diſtempers to their natural tone and conſtitution; Nature her ſelf being more prone to help on, being accompanied with an Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, her own welfare and reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to her beloved enjoyments, than to yield to the aſſaults of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Enemy.</p>
               <p>The ſecond qualities indeed are ſuch as conquer our greateſt Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſts, and give a total rout to the moſt obſtinate Diſeaſes; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt powerfully diuretical, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have attenuated, cut, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſo altered the mucous and tartarous humours of the Body, and prepared them for excretion, they then carry them off by urine, which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106707:52"/> is the moſt ſafe and effectual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance (for all ſharp and ſaline juyces eſpecially) of all other ſorts of evacuation whatſoever. This water alſo thus enriched, ferrets out ſuch latent paſſages and abſtruſe retirements of the Bowels and other parts, as other Medicines cannot reach, and after a diſcovery made, doth not only diſpoſſeſs what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural of its uſurped juriſdiction, but alſo by a corroborative and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforcive power, intitles Nature to her former right of inheritance, ſo firmly, that ſcarce any other than an act of old age can cut off the intail. 'Tis an eaſie thing for Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to raiſe doubts, make obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and laviſh out there cenſures againſt theſe Encomiums; but that work needs not ſmell of Oyl that anſwers them: Some may ſay, Oh I drunk it ſo long that it ſwell'd me all over, whoſe fault was that?
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106707:52"/> even ſo may the beſt Purgative, not finding a Body duely prepared, either naturally or by Art, fall ſhort of its performance, and in ſtead of relieving, poyſon the Body, ſwell it, and often times break out (an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental good turn) into Scabs, and other ſordid impurities of the skin. For preventing of this, and the like inconveniences, I ſhall give di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in the enſuing Chapter. In the interim I will ſet down ſuch Diſeaſes as it both prevents and cures, as <hi>Apoplexy, Epilpſie, Carus, Vertigo, Cephalalgia,</hi> and <hi>Cephalaea,</hi> but this only if they be ſymptoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and depend upon the diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Stomach, Hypochon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Womb, or other Bowels, as moſt of them do. It is good againſt Diſeaſes of the Nerves, as <hi>Convulſions, Cramps, Scorbutick Palſie, &amp;c.</hi> eſpecially if they proceed, as generally they do, from Sal-nitrous vellicating and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106707:53"/> twitching humours. It ſpecifically reſpects the Stomach, becauſe there the water partakes both of its groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and more ſpiritualized particles, diſſolves all crudities, the true o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of all obſtructions, reſtores a decayed, and advanceth a preſent Appetite to meat, and by that means begets much more acquaintance with the Kitchin than the Buttery; it openeth and ſtrengtheneth the Lungs, and conſequently is good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Aſtma's</hi> and difficulty of breathing, provided they be not conſumptive that drink it. The like it doth to the Liver, Spleen, Meſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and <hi>Pancraeas,</hi> diſperſing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon all Hypocondriacal Winds and Melancholy Vapours, which are now become our Epidemical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe; as alſo the Palpitation of the Heart, being ordinarily a reſult from the aforeſaid flatulencies and winds. It helps the <hi>Dropſie, Black</hi> and <hi>Yellow
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106707:53"/> Jaundice, Rickets,</hi> and <hi>Scurvy,</hi> by being briskly operative, purging and purifying the Blood by urine. It cures the <hi>Gonorrhea, Diarrhea, Diſenteria,</hi> and ſuch like Fluxes of the <hi>Abdomen.</hi> It openeth the ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Urin, and carries off the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct cauſe thereof, allays its ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and expells ſuch gravel and ſtones, as either the Ureters or <hi>U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retra</hi> can diſcharge; and when any Exuleration happens in the paſſage of Urine, cauſing piſſing of blood, it conſolidates and heals it perfectly. It is exceeding good againſt moſt of the Diſtempers of the Womb, ſuppreſſing all overflowings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as well the white as the red, procures the menſtruous purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and by its tenuity of parts, and penetrating Faculty, cures the <hi>Chloroſis</hi> or <hi>Green-ſickneſs,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently changeth that chachecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal colour in the habit of the body
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106707:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:106707:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:106707:55"/> into a florid and roſie complection: It helpeth much the <hi>Mother,</hi> makes often the barren fruitful, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers caſes may ſucceſsfully be uſed by way of inſeſſion or injection, for then it acts more immediately upon the parts affected. It is good for ſuch as bleed often, and whoever are troubled with a pricking and itching in the skin, with certain lumps ariſing thence, it infallibly remedies them by urine and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible tranſpiration alſo, in caſe you exerciſe whilſt you drink it, <hi>ad ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borem</hi> only, not <hi>ad ſudorem,</hi> 'till you be prety warm but not ſweat; and this I have often experienced. If you drop it into the Eyes, it quells their inflammation and ſtrengthens the ſight. Moreover it is peculiarly good for all Wounds, Ulcers, Itch, Sores, and Scabs, being both drank and outwardly applied, in ſo much as I have known divers inveterate and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106707:55"/> malign Ulcers in the Legs and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where cured, nay even the <hi>Kings Evil</hi> it ſelf much relieved thereby.</p>
               <p>Briefly, I know no Diſtemper in the Body, which depends on ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions or acid ſharp griping hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, but it much helps it, and which is moſt praiſe-worthy it ſtrengthens the parts after the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifick matter is removed. How far and how ſafely this Water may be uſed by Children, old Men, and Women with child, I ſhall refer you to Dr. <hi>French</hi> and Dr. <hi>Wittie</hi>'s Books of the <hi>Spaws,</hi> and others Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions thereon. Only I will ſay briefly, for Children and old Men, that if their temper and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be otherwiſe good, they may ſafely drink thereof, proportionably to their vigour and ſtrength of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural heat; but for Women with child, for ſome important reaſons I would adviſe them to forbear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:106707:56"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. Directions concerning the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and methodical uſe of this Spaw.</head>
               <p>'TIs a vulgar and unpardonable errour to drink theſe waters without a due preparation of the Body, therefore let every one, who expects the true benefit thereof, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult ſome honeſt and able Phyſitian for their inſtruction, ſuch an one as can judge aright of the age and conſtitution of the Patient, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Diſeaſe, its motion, and the ſtrength both of the Party and the Medicine. Such an one will ſurely direct ſome gentle Vomit, in caſe the Stomack be fowl, and the Patient hath an inclination and be
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106707:56"/> apt to Vomit; otherwiſe ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thartick, ſuch at leaſt as may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden the <hi>primas vias,</hi> and remove ſuch viſcous and vitious matter, as may either hinder the waters jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into the parts affected, or that may be carried along therewith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the narrower paſſages and nobler parts, and there produce ſtronger and more dangerous obſtructions, Dropſies, Tenſions, Gripings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet if any Purgation in general may be recommended, I dare prefer the uſe of chewing Rubarb before any other, or in caſe this diſguſt, then thoſe delicious hydragogical Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blets, which are to be had at Mr. <hi>Dents</hi> an Apothecary of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> together with the true Doſe and manner of uſing the ſame. The Body thus prepared, let him drink cheerfully about three half pint glaſſes at a time, more or leſs, as his Stomach can bear it, then exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106707:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:106707:57"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:106707:58"/> according to ſtrength for a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an hour or thereabout, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding all ſuch exerciſe as may cauſe them to ſweat, for by ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the water may be drawn into the habit of the body, and produce that Dropſie called <hi>Anaſarca;</hi> whilſt he walks or rides, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he muſt eat ſome Orange Chips, Caraway Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, Citron or Limon Pills, or chiefly Elicampane Roots candied, for theſe comfort the Stomach, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the waters paſſage, and make its operation more effectual; when he finds his Stomach ſomewhat emptied, then three or four more glaſſes, exerciſing as formerly, and ſo on 'till he hath taken his full Doſe, which will be when his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach cannot conveniently receive any more without vomiting, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and naufeating the ſame. Next day he may advance to one, two, or three glaſſes more than he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106707:58"/> took the firſt day, and ſo every day more, 'till he arrive unto a pottle or three quarts, more or leſs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as his Diſeaſe requires, and his Stomach can paſs it off, and then ſtand at that quantity 'till he thinks of giving it over, and then, as he encreaſed daily at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſo muſt he decreaſe and leſſen his Doſe, 'till he come to the ſame quantity he began withall. The time of continuing its drinking muſt be proportion'd to the nature of the Diſeaſe, for ſome two weeks, ſome three, others a month or more, may be neceſſary; during all which time, 'twill be requiſite to take ſomething to keep your Body ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble. If any one, by reaſon of his weakneſs, can neither exerciſe nor come to the <hi>Spaw,</hi> let him drink it in bed, the natural warmth thereof compenſates the benefit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by exerciſe. Now, though
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106707:59"/> this water may of it ſelf in ſome good meaſure help moſt Diſeaſes, yet can it not be thought, but for rendering it more ſucceſsful in ſome particular caſes, 'twill be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to take ſuch other things of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times as the Diſeaſe ſpecifically requires, and theſe may be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed with the firſt two or three glaſſes, <hi>v. g.</hi> ſome Steel-wine, or other Preparations thereof, in caſe of great obſtructions or other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes of the Liver, but then no more water for about half an hour after; nay I altogether admit of Sugar, or ſome opening Syrup, in the firſt glaſs, it being thereby the better accelerated to the Liver, as alſo a glaſs of White or Rheniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine mixed with three or four glaſſes of the water, or ſome drops of Spirit of Salt or Vitriol, or Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtals of Tartar, ſo that the Cryſtals be made of Tartar and not of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106707:59"/> as ſome do, for having with leſs labour the greater quantity of Cryſtals. All theſe I ſay, and ſuch like, being piercing and attenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, make way for the ſpeedy and free conveyance of the water, and of themſelves contribute much to ſome Cures.</p>
               <p>After you have drunk all you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, you muſt then neceſſarily uſe ſome hydragogical Medicine, or ſuch as evacuateth wateriſh humours, which for the moſt part remain in the abſtruſe crannies of the Body, as likewiſe ſuch things as cool and moiſten the Bowels, otherwiſe they may partake too much of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential virtue of this chalybiate wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being hot and dry, and thence incur the prejudice of Sore Eyes, and other Inflammations, as I my ſelf have experienced. Before you drink the water, every morning, disburden Nature of her ordinary
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106707:60"/> excrements, either naturally or by Art. Thoſe who have ſtrong di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions may drink half the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity in the Afternoon, about four or five hours after Dinner, but then they muſt eat little or nothing at Supper, others had better forbear.</p>
               <p>If any one find himſelf, after due preparation and ſeveral tryals, not able to drink the water, without reluctancy and oppreſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, let him forbear, and addreſs himſelf to other Remedies more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to his conſtitution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. Directions in order to Diet, and time for drinking it.</head>
               <p>THe truth is, though a regular Diet be commendable, and of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106707:60"/> great concern at all times, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when we run any courſe of Phyſick for repairing health, yet I approve not ſo much of being ſo ſceptically ſcrupulous, as many are, either in directing or obſerving ſo preciſe and narrow compaſs of Diet. The only great fear is that of exceſs, the quantity is much more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable than the quality, and the rather, becauſe the water in moſt, if not in all, begetteth <hi>appetitum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninum,</hi> a devouring appetite, ſo as Men are apt to receive more than they can well digeſt, and thence ariſe crudities and corruption, in ſtead of concoction and chylifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A temperate Diet both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents and cures many Diſeaſes, and is the chiefeſt <hi>medium</hi> we have for a laſting and poſſibly an everlaſting life; hence it is that <hi>Italians</hi> ſay, <hi>Manger molto è manger poro,</hi> who deſires to eat much muſt eat little,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106707:61"/> for by eating little he lives long, and conſequently eats much.</p>
               <p>All things that are of laudable juyce, and of eaſie digeſtion, may be admitted; I ſhall only forbid Meats too much ſalted, Geeſe, Eels, Salmon, all ſorts of fat, and in fine ſuch things as are found diſagreeable to the temper and conſtitution of the party; but if otherwiſe Nature takes delight in a Meat, though not at all proper for the Diſeaſe, yet is it allowable; and therefore <hi>Hipp. l. 2. Aphoriſm.</hi> 38. affirmeth, <hi>Paulo pejor ſed ſuavior cibus &amp; potus meliori qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſed ingrato praeferendus.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we muſt permit Meat and Drink, though ſomething worſe for the Diſeaſe, if otherwiſe it be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Your Drink alſo muſt be ſuited to your Stomach and temper, cold Stomachs may drink ſtrong Ale or Sack, hotter and ſtronger Stomachs muſt be content with ſmaller Beve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Wine diluted.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:106707:61"/>
               <p>'Tis not good to eat any thing 'till the water be moſt, if not all, paſſed thorough your Body, which is known beſt by the colour of your Urin, changing from a pale to a higher tincture. To cloſe all, as to Diet, I advife all never to eat ſo much as their appetite may crave, but, as we commonly ſay, to leave off with a ſtomach.</p>
               <p>As to the time and ſeaſon of the year, 'tis certainly then beſt (gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpeaking) when the weather is hotteſt and dryeſt, which happens moſt commonly in <hi>June, July,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt;</hi> though we have by no little coſt and labour; (having the benefit of a declivity) ſo ordered the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent parts thereof, that the Rain glides off without ſinking any wiſe conſiderably into the ground, and conſequently it may be drank in rainy weather without any apparent diminution of its virtue. I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106707:62"/> it before Sun-riſe to be incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to luke-warmneſs, which after two or three hours of a Solar influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, becomes briskly cold, which alteration is doubtleſs from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction and dilatation of the pores of the earth, locking up or venti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the fuliginous Vapours, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly as the coldneſs of the night or heat of the Sun diſpoſeth them, and therefore 'tis fitteſt to drink) it after the Sun hath by its luſtre and beams diſſipated thoſe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, and enlivened the Mineral Spirits.</p>
               <p>What further may be ſaid (in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Rabbins Revealments by <hi>Elias) reſcrvetur in adventum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sit laus Dei Patri, ſummo Chriſto decus,</l>
                  <l>Spiritui Sancto, tribus honor unus, Amen.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106707:62"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
